A Guide to the Papers of Ellen Graham Anderson, 1912-1959
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Ellen Graham Anderson 1912-1959
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-96-f
This collection consists of 300 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was gifted by Ellen Graham Andersonon 1963 July 4 (#38-96-f) and 1963 August 13(#38-96-g).
Scope and Content Information
The papers consist chiefly of drawings, chiefly pen-and-ink, by Anderson including portraits of Marietta Minnegerode Andrews, Michael Arlen, Tallulah Bankhead, James Boyd, Struthers Burt, James Branch Cabell, Jane Cowl, Beale Davis, Anna Denzler Duncan, Isadora Duncan, Amelita Galli-Curci, Ellen Glasgow, Margaret Hamilton, O. P. Heggie, DuBose Heyward, Raymond Hitchcock, De Wolf Hopper, Margaret Bell Houston, Ring Lardner, Pauline Lord, O.O. McIntyre, Ethel Merman, Victor Moore, John Powell, Maud Powell, John Cowper Powys, Yvonne Printemps, Fred Stone, Laurette Taylor, June Walker, Clifton Webb, and Helen Westley together with newsclippings of her illustrations.
In addition there are many sketches of circus performers, unidentified actors and dancers, still lifes, street scenes and houses in several southern cities, and scenes in Bermuda.
The papers also contain correspondence of William Alexander Anderson regarding the controversy over the inventor of the McCormick reaper; and miscellaneous family correspondence.
In addition there is a manuscript of a poem by Anderson entitled Goose Creek Church.
Correspondents include Anita McCormick Blane, Cyrus H. Adams, Cyrus Hall McCormick, Lyon Gardiner Tyler, Kathaleen Bruce, Virginius Dabney, E.G. Dodson, J. Albertis Harrison, Paul M. Panick and A. Willis Robertson.
Contents List
- photographic copy of pen-and-ink profile portrait of Glenna Collett, with cover letter 1928 DEC 15, from Myriam Siese of Alfred A. Knoff, publishers.
  1
- Full body pen-and-ink drawing of Emily Stevens dancing., Not dated.
  2
- Pen-and-ink drawing of (William) DeWolf Hopper (1858-1935) in "The Male Vampire.", Used by Post Magazine. The drawing has a date penciled in on the back: July 7, 1917.
  3
- Full body pen-and-ink drawing of Dudley Diggs in "Heartbreak House." n.d., Title written in upper right hand corner in pencil by author.
  4
- Pen and Ink drawing of Isadora Duncan (1878-1927) dancing to the 7th Symphony, dated 1917 (?) Written on the back in pencil is "Anderson 39 Charles St. Tel-C Isadora 1630 (?)" (see also folders #25 and 21)
  5
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Helen Westley, Drawing is stamped by the Post Magazine. "8-am Sat" is written in blue pencil in the upper right hand corner.
  6
- Five profile (head only) pencil sketches of a man. n.d., One item. There is some writing in pencil.
  7
- Pen-and-ink drawing, Title written by Anderson in pencil, "West Indian Negress carrying her wares to sell." Bermuda, 1921.
  8
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a clown dancing with a woman who appears to be dressed for ballroom dancing. n.d., Written in pencil in lower, right hand corner is "Square."
  9
- Pen-and-ink drawing with title "G[?] African" in quotations, and written above in upper right hand corner, "A West Indian Negress on the streets of Hamilton." n.d., Under signature is written "Bermuda."
  (see folder #8) 10
- Pen-and-ink drawing of child with circus animals (elephant, giraffe, and hippopotamus.) n.d., In lower right hand corner is written in pencil "Baby Hippo." On the back is written in pencil, "Circus--New York."
  11
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Raymond Hitchcock. n.d., (Title written in pencil in lower left-hand corner.)
  12
- Pencil sketch of the profile of John Powell, February 6, 1919. Written on back in pencil, "original from life by Ellen G. Anderson. The ink drawing of this was bought by Rosa Tucker Mosser (?) his cousin."
  13
- Pen-and-ink drawing of an African-American man named Bert Williams. n.d., Anderson's signature appears to have been erased. On the back of the drawing is an engraving ticket with instructions for cropping. This drawing was apparently used in an advertisement for Macy's.
  14
- Pen-and-ink drawing of an African-American man n.d., The man is bent over with his left hand on his head. Written in the upper right hand corner is the name "George Morison (?)"
  15
- Three distinct pen-and-ink scenes on one piece of paper. n.d., The top scene is of French sailors talking with each other. (see folder #19) The second is of children dancing. The third is of a man and a woman walking one behind the other. On the back is written in pencil, "E.G. Anderson 107 W. 11th (?)"
  16
- Pen-and-Ink drawing of De Wolf Hopper in "The Passing Show of 1917 (?)", Used by Post Magazine. (Also see folder #3) Description written in pencil on back of drawing.
  17
- Pen-and-Ink drawing of two circus performers. n.d., One is a trapeze artist, the other is a young woman holding onto a rope.
  18
- Pen-and-ink drawing of two French sailors n.d., Used by Post Magazine. Written in pencil in the bottom left-hand corner is "Marins--'Mois--en France'" (see folder #16)
  19
- Pen-and-ink drawing of dancer with castanets n.d.
  20
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a woman (Isadora Duncan?) dancing to the 7th Symphony. n.d., (See folders #5 and 24)
  21
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Ring Lardner. n.d., Written in pencil in bottom right-hand corner, "Ring Lardner from life. This sketch the property of Charles Scribners Sons."
  22
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Jane Cowl acting in "Vive Le France -Vive L'Annee". n.d.
  23
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Isadora Duncan in her last performance, dancing to the Vivace of the Pathetique Symphony by Tchaikowsky. n.d., Pencil written description by artist, "Isadora Duncan--suggested by her own dance in her last appearance."
  (see also folders #21 and #5) Penciled on the back are the words "return to Miss Ellen G. Anderson 308 Letcher Ave, Lexington, Virginia. Please do not cut or lose this sketch." Additional writing. n.d. 24
- Pen-and-ink sketch of Pauline Lord acting in "Anna Christie". n.d.
  25
- Two pen-and-ink sketches of Isadora Duncan on one piece of paper. n.d., Duncan is dancing to the "Allegro Vivace of the Pathetique of Tchikowsky Symphony." Anderson submitted this sketch to the Times-Dispatch. (see folders # 24, 21, and 5)
  26
- Pen-and-ink sketch of Pat McDonald, "champion weight thrower". n.d., Anderson's address and phone number on the back is written in pencil as "39 Charles St. City, Tel-Chelsea 1630".
  27
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Margaret Hamilton in "The Farmer Takes a Wife." n.d.
  28
- Pen-and-Ink drawing of two acrobats, Ira and Edward Millette, from a circus in New York. n.d.
  29
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Frances White in "Six Times Six is Thirty-six." n.d., Cropping lines indicate that drawing was published. Anderson's address and phone number are penciled in on the back of the drawing as "39 Charles st., Chelsea 1630."
  30
- Pen-and-Ink drawing of Jacques Calpeau dressed in a cape, acting in " Vieux Colombier L'Impromptu." n.d., Apparently, drawing was published.
  31
- Pen-and-ink drawing of O.P. Heggie and Laurette Taylor acting in "The Merchant of Venice." n.d.
  32
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Yvonne Printemps acting in "Conversation Piece." n.d.
  33
- Pen-and-ink drawing of William Guxton dressed as a sailor in "Anything Goes." n.d.
  34
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Maxime Elliot acting in "Lady Algy." n.d., Drawing was published by Post Magazine.
  35
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Yvonne Printemps., See folder #33.
  36
- Pen-and-ink drawing entitled "Decathlon" of Brutus Hamilton "Putting shot." n.d.
  37
- Pen-and-ink drawing of female dancer with castanets. n.d., Published by Post Magazine.
  See also folder #20. 38
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a male dancer entitled "Spanish dance: Kreutzberg." n.d.
  39
- Pen-and-ink drawing of June Walker acting in "The Farmer Takes a Wife." n.d.
  (See also folder #28.) 40
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Margaret Guglin in Greek attire, acting in "Medea." n.d.
  41
- Pen-and-ink drawing of the Vampire in "Business Before Pleasure." n.d., Drawing was apparently published.
  42
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Jacques Colpeau in Vieux Columbier, "Les Fairbenes de Scalpin.", Used by Post Magazine on December 8, 1917.
  43
- Pen-and-ink drawing of male dancer with castanets. n.d., Used by Post Magazine.
  44
- Pen-and-ink drawing., The description is written on the back by the author "Anna Denzler, one of Isadora Duncan's dancers, reappearing at Carnegie Hall." Denzler is dancing to the "Marche Militaire." In the upper right hand corner is written, "This drawing is not for sale, but may be reproduced."
  45
- Pen-and-ink profile and pen-and-ink portrait, one on each side., Both drawings are of Mr. Oscar Odd McIntyre (1884-1938), a newspaper writer.
  46
- Pen-and-ink portrait of O.O. McIntyre. n.d., Anderson 's address on the back of the portrait reads "207 Barclay Lane-- Lexington, Virginia.
  47
- Pen-and-ink profile of O.O. McIntyre, n.d., drawn from life. See also folders 46 and 47.
  48
- Pen-and-ink profile of O.O. McIntyre, n.d., drawn from life.
  49
- Pen-and-ink profile of O.O. McIntyre, n.d., drawn from life.
  50
- Pen-and-ink profile of O.O. McIntyre, n.d., drawn from life.
  51
- Pen-and-ink drawing of two clowns/actors, one male and one female, on roller skates. n.d., Drawing is entitled "Hippodrome." Anderson's address is written in the lower left-hand corner as "39 Charles St." On the back of the drawing are several rough pencil sketches.
  52
- Pen-and-ink profile of Beale Davis (1886-1929), a diplomat and author, drawn from life. n.d., Anderson's address on the back reads "10 Letcher Avenue--Lexington--Virginia."
  53
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Clifton Webb (1889-1966), a singer, dancer and motion picture actor.
  54
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Mr. James Branch Cabell, an author, drawn from life in his study on May 7th 1926., In the drawing, Mr. Cabell is reading. Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is "10 Letcher Avenue, Lexington, Virginia". Underneath her address is written "return to--Essex House, 160 Central Park S. New York."
  55
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Maud Powell, a violinist, with her violin, and standing in front of a piano., Description written by Anderson reads, "Impression of Maud Powell. Done at her apartment on Green Park (?)"
  56
- Pen-and-ink profile of Margaret Bell Houston, an author., Drawing is from life.
  57
- Pen-and-ink profile drawing of Ellen Glasgow (1874-1945), a Pulitzer prize winning author, drawn from life. n.d., Also written on drawing is "Richmond, Va. courtesy of Doubleday Page and Co." Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is 10 Letcher Ave., Lexington, Virginia.
  58
- Pen-and-ink portrait of DuBose Heyward (1885-1940), an author from Charleston, South Carolina. n.d., Drawn from life.
  59
- Pen-and-ink profile of DuBose Heyward, drawn from life. n.d.
  Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is 207 Barclay Lane, Lexington, Virginia. See also folder #59. 60
- Pen-and-ink drawing of James Boyd, from life. n.d., Penciled description: "James Boyd, Southern Pines, from life."
  See also folder #65. 61
- Pen-and-ink profile of John Cowper Powys (1872-1963), an English author. n.d., Drawing is from life.
  62
- Pen-and-ink profile of John Cowper Powys (1872-1963), from life. n.d.
  63
- Pen-and-ink profile of John Cowper Powys, from life. n.d., Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is "P.O. Box 773, Lexington, Virginia."
  64
- Pen-and-ink portrait of Struthers Burt (1882-1954) with pipe., Bert was an author from Baltimore. He died at his home in Southern Pines, North Carolina. See also folder #61. On the other side, a pen-and-ink drawing of James Boyd drawn from life at Southern Pines, March 1927.
  65
- Pen-and-ink profile of Katherine Newlin Burt, wife of Struthers Burt., (See also folder #65.) This drawing is dated "1927, Southern Pines." Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is "10 Letcher Ave. Lexington, Virginia."
  66
- Pen-and-ink profile of Katherine Newlin Burt, dated 1927. See also folders 65, 66, and 61. An address is penciled on the back of this drawing, "386--Fourth Ave.--"
  67
- Pen-and-ink profile of Michael Arlen (1895-1956), an author from Bulgaria. n.d., Profile was drawn from life in New York. Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is "Box 773--Lexington--Virginia."
  68
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Tallulah Bankhead, n.d., wife of John Hollis Bankhead, a senator from Alabama. Drawing is entitled "Dark Victory."
  69
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Tallulah Bankhead, entitled "Dark Victory." n.d., See also folder #69.
  70
- Pen-and-ink profile of Marietta Minnegerode Andrews (1869-1931), an author and painter from Washington D.C. n.d., Andrews was married to Eliphalet Fraser Andrews, the director of the Corcoran School of Art. Profile was drawn from life in Washington, D.C. Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is "308 Letcher Avenue, Lexington, Virginia."
  71
- Pen-and-ink drawing of actress Ethel Merman in "Anything Goes." n.d., Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is "207 Barclay Lane, Lexington, Virginia." See also Folders #74 and #75.
  72
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Fred Stone (1873--1959), an actor. n.d.
  73
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Victor Moore (1876-1962), an actor, in "Anything Goes." n.d., See also folders #72 and #74.
  74
- Pen-and-ink profile of Victor Moore in "Anything Goes." n.d., See also folders #72 and #74.
  75
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Elizabeth Berguer in "Escape Me Never." n.d.
  76
- Pen-and-ink portrait of a man. n.d., Two names are written in the lower right-hand corner of the drawing: Cory Ford and John Riddell.
  77
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a female dancer dancing to Brahms' "Waltz in A Major," sketched from the performance. n.d., Dancer's name is Anna Duncan (?). Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is "308 Letcher Ave. Lexington, Virginia."
  78
- Pen-and-ink drawing of Florence McGee as the "Imp" in "The Children's Hour." n.d., Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is "207 Barclay Lane Lexington, Virginia."
  79
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a dancer, Galli Curei (?) as Dimorali (?). n.d., Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is "39 Charles St., N.Y.C."
  80
- Pen-and-ink drawing of acrobats. n.d., On the left side of the drawing is the White family, two men. On the right side of the drawing are the Tybell Sisters, two women.
  81
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a female dancer dancing to Chopin's "Mazurka". n.d., Drawing was used in the Richmond Times Dispatch. Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is "308 Letcher Ave - Lexington, Virginia.
  82
- Pen-and-ink drawing of an actor dressed as a king, carrying a sword and a shield. n.d., Drawing is titled "Le Coq D'Or" (?) with the name "Bohm" (?) penciled above the title. This drawing was used by the Post Magazine.
  See also drawiing #124. 83
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a female dancer with castenets in "L'Argentina", during its first performance. n.d., Anderson's "39 Charles St." address is crossed out on the back of this drawing, and underneath is her "308 Letcher Ave. Lexington, Virginia" address. In the lower left hand corner of the drawing is penciled "For (?) before stardom."
  84
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a chair, table, and lamp. n.d., This was drawn at the Windsor Hotel, 100 W. 58th Street, City. (New York?)
  85
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a chair, table, and lamp, drawn at the Windsor Hotel. n.d., See also drawing #85.
  86
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a table, lamp, curtain, and staircase. n.d., The note on the back reads "Interior designed by self." The address is "Windsor Hotel." See also drawings 85 and 86.
  87
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a chair and table. n.d., Written in the upper left-hand corner are the words "Sloane's furniture." Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is "Windsor Hotel, 100 West 58th Street, City." See also drawings 85, 86, 97, and 88.
  88
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a moulded iron grate. n.d., Anderson predicted that the production year of the grate was about 1800.
  89
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a chair, table, and window with curtains and a cactus on the sill. n.d.
  See also drawings 85, 86, and 87. 90
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a chair, table, lamp, and bookshelf. n.d., Anderson has written "Furniture from Sloan's" in the upper left-hand corner. The address on the back of the drawing is the "Windsor Hotel." See also drawings 85, 86, 87, 88, 90, and 91.
  91
- Pen-and-ink drawing of an old iron fire grate which was manufactured by William Smoore Furnace in 1789. n.d.
  92
- Pen-and-ink drawing entitled "Sloane's Furniture, Dining Room." n.d., Address on the back of this drawing is "Windsor Hotel."
  See also drawings 85, 86, 97, 88, 89, 90, and 91. n.d. 93
- Pen-and-ink drawing of table, chair, and window. n.d., Chair is a Fortly Kiltinger design (?). Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is "the Windsor Hotel." See also drawings 85, 86, 87, 88, 89, 90, 91, 91, and 93.
  94
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a fireplace, table, chair, etc. n.d.
  95
- Pen-and-ink drawing of an unidentified dancer. n.d., Drawing is not signed.
  96
- Pen-and-ink drawing of an unidentified ballet dancer. n.d.
  97
- Pen-and-ink drawing of an actor and an actress, "Fakine (?) and Fakina (?)" in Mazurka. n.d.
  98
- Pen-and-ink drawing of an actress in "Milligan Place". n.d.
  99
- Pen-and-ink drawing entitled "Resting behind Scenes.", Drawing is of circus performers (?) A man dressed as a giraffe, "taking a smoke, " a woman in a curtain, and a dwarf clown. Dated 1922.
  100
- Floor plans of a house. n.d., Unsigned
  101
- Plans for upstairs of a house. n.d., Unsigned
  "Complete drawing of floor plan can be secured." is written in lower right hand corner. See also drawing #101. 102
- Pen-and-ink drawing entitled "Bermuda gateway and house." n.d., Unsigned
  103
- Pen-and-ink drawing of an African-American woman entitled "The Praline Woman--New Orleans." n.d., Three different addresses are written on the back of this drawing, two of which are crossed out. The first is "Park Chambers, 68-w58". the sec ond is "The Windsor--100 West 58th St", and third which is not crossed out is "207 Barclay Lane--Lexington, Virginia."
  104
- Pen-and-ink drawing of an African-American woman entitled "Old Praline Woman--New Orleans." n.d., On the back of this drawing is a pencil sketch of an unidentified man. Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is "207 Barclay Lane, Lexington, Virginia."
  105
- Pen-and-ink drawing entitled "New York Srub Women" n.d., drawn during Anderson's stay at the Windsor Hotel in New York. Written on the back of this drawing is "permanent address, Lexington, Virginia."
  106
- Unsigned pencil sketch of a window. n.d.
  107
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a scrub woman working. n.d., Drawn by Anderson in New York.
  108
- Pen-and-ink drawing of two Asian women carrying fabric, entitled "Piece-Workers." n.d.
  109
- Pen-and-ink drawings of two streets in St. Augustine, Florida. n.d., The top drawing is of the "city gates and an old street," and the second drawing is of "St. George's oldest street in St. Augustine, Fla." Unsigned
  110
- Pen-and-ink drawing entitled "Old Homes in King St., Charleston, South Carolina., Anderson has written a comment in the lower right hand corner "Showing Tudor influence, but typical Charleston piazza doors." Dated 1923.
  111
- Pen-and-ink drawing of four homes in San Antonio, Texas. n.d., Two children are sketched in pencil on the street corner in front of the homes. Unsigned
  112
- Pen-and-ink drawing (side view) of a home with a man standing in front. n.d., Drawn in San Antonio (?) See also drawing #112.
  113
- Pen-and-ink drawing entitled "Mission San Francisco De Espoda. '4th Mission' San Antonio Texas.", Anderson has written underneath title, "Built 1730, note doorway." Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is "the Windsor Hotel, New York."
  114
- Pen-and-ink drawing entitled "Old Mission Guadelupe--Juarez, Mexico.", Underneath the drawing of the Mission is a drawing of the ceiling detail in Mission Guadelupe. Anderson's address on the back of these drawings is at the Windsor Hotel.
  115
- Pen-and-ink drawing entitled "Street of 'Red Lights', New Orleans." n.d., Unsigned
  116
- Pen-and-ink drawing entitled "Typical Hooded Doorway--Old Salem College, Winston Salem, North Carolina. 1786.", Anderson's address on the back of this drawing is "207 Barclay Lane, Lexington, Virginia."
  117
- Pen-and-ink drawing. n.d., Two views of the Old Rectory--St. Peters' in St. George's Town, Bermuda.
  118
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a "West Indian Negress in Bermuda--Guinea African on Water St.", Underneath the title, Anderson has written "Water in the horse troughs must be pumped by hand to conserve the limited supply." Dated February, 1921.
  119
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a female dancer entitled "Augria Enters (?)" n.d., Dancer is performing to a Strauss Waltz.
  120
- Pen-and-ink drawings of the awning bolders of a house in New Orleans. n.d., Anderson has penciled in "See Charleston. Different."
  121
- Pen-and-ink drawing of the back door or "Mrs. Cork's (?)" house. n.d., According to Anderson, the door has "three panels in each outer side."
  122
- Two pen-and-ink sketches of a lock and a foot scraper in Winston-Salem, North Carolina. n.d.
  123
- Pen-and-ink drawing of a female dancer entitled "Bohm- Assyrian Dance." n.d., Written in the lower right-hand corner is "Courtesy of N.Y. Evening Post." See also drawing #83.
  124
- Pen-and-ink darwing of a woman dancing entitled "Lazinova (?) as Hedda Gabler." n.d.
  125
- Pen-and-ink drawing of male actor entitled "Lauratore (?) as 'Prinzivolle' in '?'" n.d., Title of performance is illegible.
  126